Guide to the Center for Documentary Studies, SNCC Legacy Project Critical Oral Histories Conference Interviews, 2016-2018 RL.11446
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Center for Documentary Studies, SNCC Legacy Project Critical Oral Histories Conference Interviews, 2016-2018
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
RL.11446
260 Files MP4 video files, JPEG image files, MP3 audio files, PDF text files, and plain text files.
75 Gigabytes
Digital videos, photographs, and transcripts documenting critical oral history conferences in 2016 and 2018, with Student Non-violent Coordinating Committee veterans, hosted by the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University. The 2016 Critical Oral Histories Conference focused on "The Emergence of Black Power, 1964-1967," while the 2018 Critical Oral Histories Conference focused on the efforts directly leading to the Voting Rights Act of 1965.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
In 2013, the SNCC Legacy Project and Duke University formed the SNCC Digital Gateway in order to chronicle the historic struggles for voting rights and to develop ongoing programs that contribute to a more comprehensive understanding of SNCC efforts in the broader Civil Rights Movement during the 1960s.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Center for Documentary Studies, Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) Critical Oral Histories Conference Interviews were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016 and 2019.
Related materials
Joseph A. Sinsheimer Papers, 1962-1987
Guide to the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee 40th anniversary conference videocassette tapes, 2000
Faith Holsaert Papers, 1950-2011
Judy Richardson Papers, 1963-2014
Charlie Cobb Interviews, 2012-2013
Collection Overview
Digital videos, photographs, and transcripts documenting critical oral history conferences in 2016 and 2018, with Student Non-violent Coordinating Committee veterans, hosted by the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University. The Critical Oral Histories Conference in 2016 and 2018 were an extension of the SNCC Legacy Project that placed SNCC veterans in conversation with scholars using primary source materials. The events were produced by the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University and the SNCC Legacy Project. Series One contains the 2016 Conference interviews, in which narrators focused on the years 1964-1967, to discuss the emergence of "Black Power" as an ideological concept as well as political and economic framework. Participants included Charlie Cobb, Courtland Cox, Gloria House, Phil Hutchings, Jen Lawson, Charles McLaurin, Cleve Sellers, Shirley Sherrod, Karen Spellman, Judy Richardson, Maria Varela, Geri Augusto, Emilye Crosby, Worth Long, Hasan Jeffries, Betty Mae Fikes, Bertha O'Neal, John O'Neal, Michael Simmons, and Zoharah Simmons. Series Two contains the 2018 Conference interviews, in which narrators focused on the efforts directly leading to the Voting Rights Act of 1965, with participants including Phillip Agnew, Geri Augusto, Rebecah Barber, Kenneth A. Campbell, Charles Cobb, Courtland Cox, Emilye Crosby, Amber Delgado, David (Dave) Dennis, Sr., Ajamu Dillahunt, Hasan Kwame Jeffries, Timothy (Tim) L. Jenkins, Edwin King, Dorie Ann Ladner, Jennifer Lawson, Danita Mason-Hogans, Miles McKeller-Smith, Charles McLaurin, Ambria McNeill, Aja Monet Bacquie, Janet Moses, Robert Moses, Edna Watkins Muhammad, Quinn Osment, Timothy B. Tyson, Hollis Watkins, and Curtis Wilkie.
Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); Civil rights movements -- Southern States; Black power -- United States; Audiovisual materials; Video recordings; Oral histories (document genre); Civil rights movements -- United States; Cobb, Charles E., Jr.; Cox, Courtland, 1941-; McLaurin, Charles; Sellers, Cleveland, 1944-; Sherrod, Shirley, 1948-; Long, Worth W.; Richardson, Judy; House, Gloria, 1941-; Hutchings, Phil, 1942-; Lawson, Jennifer, 1946-; Crosby, Emilye; Jeffries, Hasan Kwame, 1973-; Fikes, Betty Mae; O'Neal, John, 1940-; Simmons, Gwendolyn Zoharah
- Interviews, July 9 and 11, 2016
  - Day one, July 9, 2016
    - COH Day 1 part 1.mp4, 01:41:22 (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-01)
    - COH Day 1 part 2.mp4, 04:04:56 (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-01)
    - AudioDay1ThroughLunch.mp3 (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-04)
    - AudioDay1AfterLunch.mp3 (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-04)
    - Critical Oral Histories Transcript.pdf (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-01)
  - Day two, July 11, 2016
    - COH Day 2 part 1.mp4, 02:02:19 (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-01)
    - COH Day 2 part 2.mp4, 03:59:41 (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-01)
    - AudioDay2.mp3 (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-04)
    - Critical Oral Histories Transcript.pdf (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-01)
  - Edited video clips, July 9-11, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-03)
    Scope and Contents
    Short clips from videos, including Phil Hutchings on civil rights to freedom movement; Charles McLauren intro; Courtland on Us Colored People; Charlie Cobb and Gloria House on the culture of SNCC; Charlie Cobb on the Black Panther; Michael Simmons on Sexism; Charles McLauren on overcoming fear; Charlie Cobb on the impact of black power in the north; Courland on the importance of the black power mindset; Courtland on block voting; Courtland on race and class; Courtland on violence; Gloria House on the development of black consciousness and independence; Karen Spellman on black power to self-determination; Karen Spellman on culture shift in D.C. '65; Karen Spellman on sexism; Maria Varela on the popularity of black power; Michael Simmons on challenges; Michael Simmons on organizing oppressed people; Shirley Sherrod on overcoming fear; Charlie Cobb on SNCC redefining itself through black power; Cleve Sellers on movement transition to SNCC; Jennifer Lawson on layers of change leading to black power; Jennifer Lawson on the black power mindset; Shirley Sherrod on recognition of SW Georgia; Zoharah Simmons on the periods of SNCC.
  - Photographs, July 8-10, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-02)
  - Conference dossier, July 9-11, 2016 (Folder 1)
    Contains copies of primary sources collected at repositories that hold documents related to SNCC history. The dossier was used as a point of reference and discussion throughout the interviews.
- Interviews, June 15-17, 2018
  - Day one, June 15, 2018
    - Session 1 video file (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-05, Video-file Day1S1_Video.mp4)
    - Session 1 transcript (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-05, Object Day1S1_Video.txt)
    - Session 2 video file (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-05, Video-file Day1S2_Video.mp4)
    - Session 2 transcript (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-05, Object Day1S2_Video.txt)
  - Day two, June 16, 2018
    - Session 1 video file (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-05, Video-file Day2S1_Video.mp4)
    - Session 1 transcript (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-05, Object Day2S1_Video.txt)
    - Session 2 video file (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-05, Video-file Day2S2_Video.mp4)
    - Session 2 transcript (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-05, Object Day2S2_Video.txt)
  - Day three, June 17, 2018
    - Session 1 video file (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-05, Video-file Day3S1_Video.mp4)
    - Session 1 transcript (Digital-materials RL11446-SET-05, Object Day3S1_Video.txt)